good afternoon everyone
my name is Gabriel from elavandi and I'm
your host for today's green shoots
before we start I would like to thank
our venue host Prudential I must say
it's a really lovely venue this place in
terms of how it's set up and everything
it's almost perfect for such an
in-person you know gathering for green
shoots potential is also a member of
elevantes advisory committee which
includes a group of companies such as
ant group tencent tamasi crypto.com
circle UOB MasterCard and I capital
elevante is a non-profit and we're
created by the Mas just last year our
mission was put forth by senior Minister
Damon as well as the Mas board such as
Deputy Prime Minister Hing as well as
Deputy Prime Minister Wong
our mission to foster a open dialogue
between the private and public sector to
advance fintech in the digital economy
our chairman subnandu is probably
somewhere here
is also the Mastermind of the largest
world largest fintech Festival which is
coming up in November
just a brief background on green shoots
green shoots is a great grassroot
initiative that evolved in response to
the circuit breaker in the year 2000 in
our sessions introduce new announcements
products reports such as the digital for
100 report by Prudential and policies to
the financial services community
we are very excited today to hear from
our group of esteem panelists and
speakers who over here around topics on
digital wealth and micropensions it is a
topic that's very close to my heart ever
since I went through my own fa
certification process a few years back I
wouldn't say which company yeah but it's
not Prudential
since SFS reception Inception the annual
theme is carefully selected to reflect
the prevailing opportunities as well as
challenges in the financial sector
this year we will welcome 60 000 people
Global attendees in person to Singapore
to address the theme around building
resilient business models
the fintech industry currently is
undergoing through a major stress cycle
and at the Festival this year we will
deconstruct the very essence of what it
means to be a resilient business model
we will bring together stage on stage
world leaders who will share deep
insights on how to build up this kind of
business models to weather the storm
I'd like to welcome everyone to the
festival from the second or 4th of
November to join us on this journey to
create new opportunities Investments as
well as Partnerships
for those who are interested Keen to
share your expertise we have this
initiative called pay it forward it is
an educational initiative at the
festival to bring together industry
mentors Founders professionals as well
as students to navigate a changing
industry of financial Industries so
these are 30-minute one-on-one sessions
and all the details is available on our
website really whatever needs that you
have we've got you covered
with that it's my pleasure to pass the
time over to our host from Prudential
Thomas Chief Information as well as
technology officer Prudential Singapore
to share his welcome note Thomas please
[Music]
hello good afternoon to everyone thank
you for coming to uh and joining us
today in the afternoon
my name is Thomas kortrek I am chief
information and transformation office
and Technology officer at production of
Singapore I started my career actually
outside of the insurance but past 10
years I spent trying to transform
insurance
first of all from inside out within the
industry on the career side but as well
as working
outside in through the ecosystem as
founder advisor engineering vessel but
as well as through my involvement in
organization like Singapore fintech
Association try to draw it and build it
into take the insurance to the next
stage and make it more accessible for
for everyone
I have been very lucky throughout my
career
because I have been given opportunity to
live and work in more than 20 countries
but through this experience one thing
really stuck with me the fact that
wherever you are independent with in
which culture you you you live in but as
well as the people that you interact
that are always two things that are
present and on top of Mind of every
everyone
which is wealth and health
and today we are talking a topic for our
today's discussion is actually
micropensions and wealth
you might think that especially looking
from the perspective of Singapore Macho
markets
you can't pick two more distant topics
to discuss which is micro pensions and
wealth
but actually if you think about it it is
all about the spectrum that you look at
because those two things cannot coexist
without one without each other
and today what we see through our own
research interacting with the market in
Singapore but as well as across the
group that actually what we need to do
is provide solutions that increase
access but as well as make it make it
easier for customers to deliver the
ultimate and Noble promise of insurance
which is to provide protection and
resilience we're at the point of time
where I think for the first time in the
history
we are we have opportunity to build at
scale relationship with our customers
and larger community Through the device
that it sits within you with every
single one of you in your pockets and
most probably you have heard at the
beginning we just launched our digital
400 report and it's very evident that
people are confident and at ease to
manage the health
wealth but as well as overall well-being
that includes as well mental well-being
moving forward to the uh when we when
they will be ready to leave hundreds
hundred years
and this is what we are trying to do as
well as Prudential utilizing our
Solutions and Technology like pulse and
hopefully this is you'll be able to
learn much more from our panelists that
will be joining us on the stage and we
will have a great discussion about how
we can really deliver and exceed
delivery on the value and the promise of
the insurance so I would like to welcome
all the panelists and I hope that we're
going to enjoy the discussion thank you
[Music]
tough
how are you very good thank you how's
everybody doing today
great my name is Michael Wades for
people that don't know me and I do also
want to thank everybody for coming to
the screen shoots conversation and I say
I don't say the word conversation
lightly I want to give a little bit of
my own introduction I want to keep this
as interactive as possible I don't think
anybody wants to just sit there and
listen to all five of us talk so we'll
be moderating this conversation but even
before we go to the closed door session
that will not be recorded if during our
conversation anybody here has questions
or you just want to add something I mean
everybody here is interested otherwise
you wouldn't be here just raise your
hand and we'll try to get a microphone
over to you
to start okay and before we do start I
just want everybody here to give a
little bit of an introduction George
you're furthest away why don't you start
first okay just a quick one from me so
good afternoon everybody really really
happy to be here with you I'm George
kestelman uh some of you might know me I
spent a lot of time in the in short Tech
ecosystem right from the early days that
I was studying uh here in in Asia
my journey have taken me across the
world I would say and I grew up in
Canada but been in Asia for past 14
years funny enough actually it was
Prudential that brought me to Asia many
many years ago when I first came I
joined them in Hong Kong and then in
Singapore and then made my journey
through the rest of the Asia and spend
time with General Insurance life
insurance and then last seven years I've
been all around the ensure Tech
ecosystem so I started in short Tech
Asia Association uh in 2015 2016 we've
grown and in the last two years I've
also joined Zhong Tech which is a part
of Zhong group some of you might know
that this is the one of the biggest
online insurance companies in the world
and then I'm actually Chief commercial
officer for the attack arm of it super
so maybe you can give a little bit of
your background people know you I think
most but why don't you tell us something
about you I think Michael the way I
respond to a question not telling who am
I but telling what I do for a typical
day go for it okay to the morning I got
up at eight I go to early uh 8 30 I had
a meeting with Washington DC talking
about uh there's a plan this year this
week I'm in U.S tonight I'm flying to
talk about my intervention on regulatory
consideration for digital asset all the
crypto got it and then followed by a
preparation for a particular AI program
we are launching in at the fintech
festival and I had bunch of technical
senior technical people talking about
the code base how this will be
integrating for responsible AI
and before this I was sitting with the
chef And discussing the menu for
Singapore fintech festival and the and
the debate was what kind of Indian food
we should cater to and uh what was your
answer yeah no the problem is the 2016
we made a particular Biryani which was
very popular and after that it has been
not that popular so we're trying to
understand what went wrong are you a b
testing this or maybe using a little bit
of artificial intelligence to figure
this out so so we debate on that and we
landed on not a not a non-vegetarian
food so I suggested if you are Indian
you understand here A kadi chawl or a
rajma chawal or a Dal chawal in three
days and because it's kind of vegetarian
light almost a comfort food for many
Indians we can take care of that so
that's my job before coming here so now
I'm here talking about the fin micro
pension and very serious topic so that's
what I do for living that sounds awesome
can we assume that the discussion about
the food was the most discussion is
because the chef was particularly upset
when I told him that instead of that
chicken wing in a certain way can I
convert it to a Texas style and he just
responded very angrily it'll be very
messy to serve it in a big the 5000
people okay okay okay let's play with we
stay with that the trials and
tribulations yeah yeah really hard so
Thomas you've already basically
introduced yourself if that's okay Peru
um nice to be here thank you for having
us to Prudential and Tomas I'm parul
Khanna I work for an organization called
pinbox uh pinbox stands for pension in a
box so have been doing pension inclusion
as I would call it more than micro
pensions and I think ahead we will also
Define that but the work that we do is
essentially around how do you match
financial services and social protection
and provide all sorts of Social Security
Solutions uh focused around long-term
savings and pensions for those in the
informal sector Workforce and defining
informal is those where there isn't a
formal employee an employee relationship
we've been working with governments in
Asia and Africa we're currently working
in India Rwanda Kenya uh Uganda Nigeria
Papua New Guinea and starting in
Bangladesh so it sounds quite fancy but
it's not because it's the hardest task
and I think in the hardest business that
we could ever be is in pension inclusion
so that's what I do nice to meet you all
here
thank you so I'd like to start with
definitions you said a little bit that
you wanted to Define this as well can
you give a good definition for for me
and for everybody here what micro
pensions are it's actually quite
straightforward like I said I did give a
little bit out where there isn't a
formal employer employee relationship
and people save for their pensions on a
voluntary basis
um defined as informal other informal
person could be a doctor working for
himself right it could be an SME or a
um an Android just somewhere in a
village uh it could be a gig worker
anybody who is working for themselves
and are able to match their income
according to their uh pension
contribution so you cannot mandate and
say that you have to put in every month
because the farmer makes money twice a
year a gig worker makes money every day
every day so you need to match that and
that's what is microvention so this is
actually for everybody here but how do
we and maybe we can start with you
George
when we talk about financial inclusion
when we talk about insuretech at scale
and when we talk about micropensions
we're trying to figure out how do we use
technology
to be able to scale this stuff and if
all these relationships are informal
then how do we get the technology to
them to create this technological
inclusion to have the impact for micro
pensions that we want
I think the the answer to that one is
that it's still in the process of being
evolving the I think the reality is that
because of the nature of how the economy
is progressing towards the internet
economy and the growth in the digital
there is going to be a lot more things
that will need to be embedded within
those digital ecosystems so rather than
building something that let's say is a
it's an app that somebody has to
download to start the pension and to
save towards it it is going to be very
much leveraging those existing
ecosystems like ride sharing or all
those kind of other things that the the
people already there within those
ecosystems and the insurance
is basically exchanging from being a
standalone industry to becoming
something that much more very enabling
and integral part of the other uh
ecosystems and that's a big shift that's
happening from a technology perspective
as well as from the the mindset
perspective as well so sometimes you're
shaking your head yes do you want to
give us your opinion on this so one of
the challenges is the how people
perceive pension and insurance
ah I mean till varied as near past I can
say it is still sold as an investment
product
that is that that is single biggest
cultural difference we want to get over
it is a risk management product you're
buying Insurance you're buying pension
is to protect your long-term risk or a
short-term risk or immediate risk and I
think your title is towards longevity
it's all about that yeah as you as you
think about your life five year ten year
30 year time Horizon unit risk product
risk coverage product unless you
recognize that in that context very hard
for this industry to become what it
stands for but but George makes a really
good point right in the old days the
insurance industry kind of Sat by itself
and to be fair almost every industry Sat
by itself but with the onset of
Technology at scale what we're seeing is
this kind of merging now right the
ecosystem is actually really do matter
and I'm Thomas I want to get to you on
this from an insurance provider
perspective but how do you change the
mindset of big companies and even
Regulators to say before this was
separate and this was separate and this
didn't even exist but now how do we get
those things to work together so that
the underserved who are the ones that
actually need micro pensions can
actually get served
I think the answer is simple but
execution is difficult go ahead because
it all starts with the customer
and understanding of the customer and
thinking from the first principle
perspective what do we need to do to
provide the protection for for the
person yeah and when we talk about
especially micro pension it's
we need to put this in a context because
we're in Singapore so we have at least
multi multi-layered safety nets
typically people who have their own
insurance they will have savings they
will have a government government
schemes but in the countries where
people don't have uh the system doesn't
exist they have only one safety net
which is either savings or family or
family right and if something happens
like the original ecosystem exactly
sorry go ahead exactly and
if any any bad things happens actually
it might impact people for future
generation even they might hinder the
people and ability to progress and
generate wealth yeah I mean over the
future Generations I had a conversation
with a guy in India who runs this thing
called impact Guru and he's he said to
me most Indian families are one medical
emergency away from poverty it's not
only India I know I know just as an
example sorry go ahead
I read the statistics that actually in
overall Asia
the most frequent
reason for personal bankruptcy yeah is
is medical of medical
care and
medical emergencies so coming back to
your question
I think especially in Africa we have a
lot of different examples where coming
where the products are distributed
through the native
existing ecosystems or networks starting
from the from the mobile operators
because you need to go where the
customer is because let's let's be
honest one of the biggest uh challenges
for insurance to grow is to overcome the
risk awareness to understand or that
people actually needs protection right
and this is and if you combine two
things try to convince people through
the new channels but as well as explain
them that they actually need the
insurance you're making it very
difficult for for customers and yourself
as an insurer or distributor of the
products uh products to do it and we we
partner in Ghana with uh with companies
to distribute same we launch a product
in Kenya following the same same mindset
but the push was the push is not going
to come from
the insurance industry
is going to come from the ecosystem
that's the key difference now that it's
coming this way right so the people who
are going to push for it are people are
selling Health product
Medical Services people or people are
selling uh whatever the the product and
they want to bring customers and bring
coverage to the risk they bring to the
product market so I suspect it is the
ecosystem will drive that merger not the
insurers themselves so can I ask you
this you you gave a really interesting
explanation this morning already about
what your day was like yeah right so you
start your day by talking to somebody in
Washington DC these are probably senior
level people at some other authority
right so you're talking to them and
their lives are different than the
people that that we're talking about
here that need micro pensions so I'm
really curious how you think it's
different in emerging Asian markets
right because Singapore itself
I mean it's a wealthy country right so
how do you think about it in the context
of what's different between what's
happening in Singapore where pick a
number you know better than I do 30 40
50 of the population is not native and
probably do need micro pensions but the
other half don't and then the rest of
Southeast Asia India and Africa what's
the difference well I'll defer that
answer the question to apparel because
it deals with this problem day and night
but I'll give us from my perspective
yeah we do look things Beyond Singapore
uh I mean it's a strange thing that uh
it actually uh the the
one elegant way to explain that this is
that when uh traditionally
there's a say there's always a saying to
remind us that poor people don't need
poor Solutions okay yeah so so so for
when you are dealing with a low income
segment the single uh ex they have the
largest they are the most widest
expectation of risk coverage and the
product design or the underwriter for
providing the product have the least
understanding of how to cover them right
so so poorer you are wider is your
expectation wider is your risk your your
likelihood of hitting that risk
and your premium prices are exactly
opposite right so so I don't answer so
the answer should be heard because how
do price with the widest risk and most
likely to happen with a little premium
to cover that risk so that's the problem
today well it's actually two or more
than two problems but we can get to
pricing in a second but actually in a
way more interesting to me is
how do you have these disconnected
ecosystems get to people to have the
awareness that they actually need this
product but then also The Literacy for
lack of a better term to even understand
what that product is and make a choice
sure if I can just take a step back to a
few things that we touched upon I think
to understand micro pensions it is
equally relevant for Singapore as it is
for any developing country go for it
across Asia Africa Latin America from
the recent report that I just um I think
that's going to come out there were a
few studies that were very very
interesting that I saw in there
the government of Singapore incentivizes
companies to
yeah
is that better
is it on can you hear me yeah okay so
they're incentivizing to uh employ the
elderly because routinely people are
living longer but the where is the money
coming from is from the tax benefits
that people in the room pay here and
perhaps the younger generation right so
it's and one third of the population in
Singapore which is gig workers or there
are domestic workers who require micro
pensions now if you switch this to any
country in Latin America Africa or Asia
um by 2050 there will be 2 billion
people who will be above the age of 60.
now that is going to be more than the
number of people who are going to be
below the age of 15 at that time so the
problem is really big
um the cost or the opportunity of doing
something like this which means that out
of these two billion people 1.8 billion
people of these elderly will live in
developing countries
if you were to give two dollar a day
pension which is absolutely
minuscule to 1.7 of these people you
will be spending 40 trillion dollars out
of your budgets which is not a
possibility for any government but the
reverse side is that the opportunity is
so big that in the workforce there are
1.8 billion people who are eligible to
get pensions or micro pensions either
ways if one-fourth of these people get
two dollar a day pension
you can generate 10 trillion in the next
10 years so that's the compounding power
and this that's just how savings work
and pensions works as a product
how do you deliver it I think what is
most important is first to understand
what the problem is the problem is
around friction right so how do you get
people to get onboarded to open accounts
there are language barriers there are
kyc issues there are digital inclusion
and so on and so forth uh the second
thing is around the mismatch around tax
incentives matching pension
contributions the third is around lack
of digital
pension Tech which works different from
insurance
to have that kind of technology to
deliver to reduce costs
um the fourth is around people being
actually under insured which is a huge
problem the reason I say this is because
um they are meeting their emergency or
aspirational requirements through
savings or they're taking loans now
loans are good as long as you're
creating an asset everything everybody
knows it better than I do in this room
but if you're not then what they are
doing is they're eating up their savings
and they're mortgaging their future
income and that is not a very good
outcome as far as technology or as far
as pensions is concerned because they
will never be able to meet that and if
you do not match insurance with pensions
or shorter term savings with pensions
the idea of Pensions is fantastic right
I think after the pandemic God children
and kismat are not exactly very strong
retirement portfolios right people
understand that there is a need to save
for the long term but even if that is a
reality for me and including everybody
in this room and I'm and if you change
your occupations to being domestic
workers and gig workers you will not
have that Horizon in your head because
you have so many interim needs that need
to be taken care of and which can be
taken through insurances whether it's if
you're a farmer you should have cattle
insurance or weather insurance or
whatever else which are relevant to your
occupation be able to give smaller
savings instruments so that your
internal needs are taken care of only
then will they be able to save for a
longer term is there a GDP per capita
trigger
where it moves from being just sort of I
just want to survive financially I want
to be able to eat and get shelter to
actually Financial Wellness you know
what I mean and is it different between
countries but you understand what I mean
right in other words if I only have a
thousand dollars a year I don't have a
lot of time to worry about how do I deal
with my pension where do we need to get
to and I was told once by a guy who's
building a bank in the Philippines that
is around 3 725 a year in emerging
market economies but I'm just curious
what people think about is there a
trigger and then what changes you know
it's the answer is not so simple and
this isn't right the reason I say this
is because you need to understand who
the customer is people who are dissavers
or earn thousand dollars a day the
government should take care of them
because we need to understand that the
informal sector Workforce is not a human
homogeneous variety they also have lower
income and higher income in that income
group most of the Emerging Markets are
moving towards a larger middle class
which gives better buying far those are
the people that we need to look after if
you're going to go for a farmer who's
not good so for him GDP per capita or
you know inconsequential words or it's
not even significant in their lives
right right so it can't be one size fits
all it just cannot be but you need to
have opportunities for those who are
capable of the gig worker whether in
Singapore or in India or in Rwanda they
all want to make because make money and
they want to save in markets that's the
kind of awareness because they're
sitting in the car and all every all the
passengers are talking about is capital
markets and Investments so there
aspirationals they have a smartphone you
should be targeting those right why are
we trying to do a blanket cover for
everybody that even the self-help group
woman who's earning ten dollars a month
should be saving two dollars she cannot
no she cannot so I think that that could
be a counter Force going here what
happens most of the time when there's to
your point if I have thousand dollar
maybe less less My worry is not pension
and the immediate risk is covered by a
phrase called direct benefit transfer
direct benefit transfer which
essentially a state giving money free
free money to get you through the
challenges I think that there's an
opportunity to structure the diet
benefit transfer to take a portion of
the money and allocate to a long term
wealth protection long-term long-term
pension protection yeah as against a
complete handout you spend what you want
to do based on your immediate crisis so
is this where something like Central
Bank digital currencies come into play
that is one of the use case that's a
good point that's one of the use case
because if you can program them yeah we
can program the money to that you can't
use for something else other than this
purpose right so there's a purpose we
call it programmable purposeful money
right okay so I think part of that uh
your question is not of course there's a
literacy opportunity you can tell people
doesn't matter how much you earn a
fraction of that that is still worth it
worth the contribution I mean
compounding matters in all cases yeah
but
most of the time politicians who respond
to that crisis with their DVT that that
benefit transfers yeah and that kind of
differs that problem statement but here
the opportunity to restructure that
particular Behavior to make it uh what
you want to do I'm sorry
no I would like to add maybe one more
solution which is stock up protection
because that's that's something that is
much easier to implement and benefits
from governments either from the
governments or or the population level
yes because
once again it's all about protecting
about those fail risks the big risk and
because this is what hurts people for
generation and this is much easier even
when you talk about the uh with program
of money it's quite easy to do it
because if you know how much people are
spending on a specific category of
expense then then you can start kicking
and it's solves the problem so sorry
when I was just go ahead there are
examples of doing this so only for
pension inclusion uh countries like
India already incentivize the youth to
save for the pensions the reason is
if you you'd rather spend that money
today than be able to give them old age
pension because it's much more expensive
to give meaningful payouts but to have
incentives today Governor Rwanda started
this uh in fact we'd worked them on the
policy side as well uh they ran a
program on micropensions three years ago
where they match
um
according to the income categories
without going to those details they give
about 50 to 30 depending on the income
category that you're in they match it
and they also give funeral insurance as
a and a life insurance cover as a
benefit to people for the first three
years for savings so funeral Insurance
works well because as a nation funeral
expenses are a matter of dignity and
last rights right so they match it up
and people kind of see value in that
government of Uganda also gives
incentive government of Kenya gives
guaranteed returns so these are all bad
policy matters that already exist and
these are incentives that again g2p
transfer direct transfers already exist
even on micropensions I want to come
back to this because we already talked
about Central Bank digital currencies it
opens up a whole conversation about
I don't want to say cryptocurrency I
just really want to talk about
distributed Ledger technology I want to
leave the speculation to the speculators
because frankly I don't care about it to
be fair but is there a self-sovereign
data issue here as well where if you can
if everyone has a mobile phone and they
understand the way that technology works
this is anybody can answer this
is there a way to give people ownership
of their own data to make it easier for
them to have a whole array of financial
services including micropensions go
ahead
well I think this has been but that's a
long-term view on this whole whole
design the I think that if you are going
to
if all of us are going to participate on
the future design
where we are a participant in the
network
and the transfer of value whether for
pension or what are personal services is
going to be bilateral between two party
with no intermedies in between of course
self-solvent ID becomes the Cornerstone
of that architecture which means all of
us should be visible identifiable in the
network status step one step two you
need a certain currency to power this
network because there is a need for
incentive to ensure that person
validates these two people are
exchanging ownership and value in that
in that transaction and third you need a
new form of money which will power this
transactions between two parties against
the uh as as against today where
when I pay somebody
for buying your this particular laptop
the delivery happens in a different
process at the two different processes
yeah the act of paying an act of
ownership of the laptop is two different
processes yeah they're not related so
the to your question when you're talking
about this new model It all becomes a
single transaction the moment and that
is a token a token ownership transfers
value get exchange ownership get
exchanged so I think in this new design
you you will see a far better I would
say far better technology platform to
solve a wide range of financial sector
sector issues from three ways it reduces
the cost of transfers second it
increases the transparency of the or the
participating population and third it is
far more uh
it is driven to the value of the
participant on the network
to explain that today when I when you do
a Google search suppose I am searching
parul
for whatever reason I would write a I'm
going to write an article right I go to
Google I type parul Khanna and I get all
her last speeches her YouTubes
what else he has done yep and I don't
pay her for doing that yep
in the future design all of us will get
into the search engine the first step
after giving your name and detail will
be a wallet which includes some new form
of money
what happens that when I search parole
automatically parallel gets credited a
small fraction of my digital money
because I searched her because I am
taking a value from her contribution on
the network I think that's the future we
are talking about right and it's it
requires there to be the self-sovereign
data ownership yes yes because she has
to be the owner of her yes yes but
here's the thing right
all of us understand that yes but how do
you get the farmer who's worried about
just crop failure to understand because
they are participating in the network I
get it I get it yes but how do they know
that that's the benefit to them go ahead
because I'm really curious about I don't
know how they know that does the example
little finish there's an example that so
um there are a couple of examples of
that as well right I think public good
is already made in terms of uh
especially in countries like India and a
few in Africa where there is public
Awareness on you know open your bank
accounts don't share your OTP don't give
your personal pii information sure you
know so on and so forth but I have to
tell you that do not underestimate that
farmer right until 10 years ago we had
an example where uh ATM cards were
issued and there was a guy from on top
of the hill took every 20 people
everybody's phone or ATM cards
everybody's pin was one two three four
he went down the hill put everybody's
Cards into the ATM withdrew the money
that he wanted and he charged a fee of
20 rupees right or each one of them
right but now the alternative is that
that same individual whose bank account
is linked to his aadhaar in India or any
national ID or m-pesa in Kenya is not
doing that right because the public good
awareness has been created for an
ecosystem for financial services to be
added so this is the reason why I asked
this question because I want people to
understand
that this information is actually is
actually getting disseminated as far
away as possible and this is the big
benefit of having as Thomas said that
computer in your pocket yes and this now
gives the ability to do what supplementu
just just suggested but I want to make
it clear that that's the case that there
is somebody in that community and
getting back to this idea of ecosystems
that knows that so to to dismiss them
out of hand is one of the mistakes it's
not going to be possible in the new
models because Ms but Ms has started a
program with Central Bank of Ghana or
we're also talking to one country in
Asia I can publicly say that where we
are coming with a project called
verifiable credential yep it's called
verifiable credential the project in a
simpler way this is how it's designed
today in cashion while 70 percent of all
food supply comes from small and
marginal Farmers let's not forget that
we are quite comfortable because many
aggregators are aggregating Food
Supplies smallholder farmers and coming
to that in fact I found out last year
there is a most of us today when we get
suppose an importer in Singapore when
they import food from this country
they're at the fourth level of
aggregation
so there's a fourth aggregator there is
a third aggregator the second aggregator
first aggregator then the farmers right
that's how the food chain work it's
pretty amazing right yeah so and there
are Traders here who are holding
contracts paper contracts against those
aggregators very complex model yep but
70 of real food supply comes from this
marginal Farmers yeah now the program
which Ms is doing in partnership with
the Central Bank of Ghana we have taken
a two use case cashew nut and saw cashew
nut and soy wind Farmers the idea is to
every marginal farmer will participate
in the network and they will get a token
called verifiable credential and the
token is nothing to their ability to pay
is about intent to pay because if I have
intent to pay because they are doing the
real farming they are doing they are
taking workshops they're getting
certificates that token becomes the way
to get credit from the bank right and
they also use the same data set I will
send it to the and the the the the
people who provide medicine for this for
the crops insurers and they can use the
same token to cross sell the product to
them so now you have created digital
footprint at the lowest level to create
a new economic model right so let's back
up now and tie this all back together to
the insurance industry and then I want
to bring it back to health Tech again in
a second but now that we're doing this
now that the monetary authority of
Singapore is partnering with the
government of Ghana to do this in the
cashew and what was the other one
percent soy right you're creating this
program now it's incumbent upon
incumbent was probably the wrong word
but it's incumbent upon the big insurers
and the insured tax to say how do we
participate in the tokenization of the
protection for them
data set that's my point though right is
how do we how do we we do that to test
it out and then expand that
so I fully agree because it starts with
utility and actually providing identity
is utility Beyond Insurance because
access to the financing to the broader
ecosystem spans across health and so on
so it's as soon as soon as we have a
data that trusted data and trusted
identity the rest is
simple but difficult to execute yeah
from this perspective because
especially if it's all in the machine
readable format independent if it is in
a DLT or non-dlt as long as the data
someone can no longer is there providing
adding a model that will be able to
assess the risk and price the risk is
relatively straightforward and plus
through the ecosystem that everyone is
using those tokens and the information
from the fertilizers vendor from the
distributor and so on you have open
additional channels to educate and
distribute protection and my and more
importantly this token and not control
of me exactly the farmer decide whom to
share the token again well that's the
ecosystem is getting built at the ground
level right yes and that's super
important and if you bring it all
together with the regulator Regulators
that want to the focus on the market
development they can build into the
system that's X percentage will be saved
automatically from the transaction or be
match the type of the matching matching
schemes where X will be safe and will be
much of the of the either the government
or some other entities and this is how
you keep the ball running and and create
the Snowball Effect but
we all know it's just we are not all you
know generation it needs a lot of ground
up what do you call as a digital
footprint yeah a lot of digital
footprint has to be created can we agree
here though that this is a really
Incredible use of government power to be
able to affect change I think the you
know this model we have been trying for
last three years of course and it became
possible because of one decision taken
by Ghana's government circles provide
first loss guarantee the first loss
guarantee that for the people who are
borrowing uh as long as long as they use
this model they'll provide the first
loss guarantee for any credit loss right
once you provide the government safety
structure against a proper behavior then
everything becomes easier because
everybody wants to participate yes
because they feel safer I mean risk
mitigation is a real thing right so
that's that's that turned around truly
interesting George can you talk about
this a little bit just from an insurance
and insured Tech perspective about how
now that you see all this stuff
happening what is the product creation
stuff look like just to bring it back to
here
something from a product creation
standpoint again there's two layers one
is the actual product of insurance or
pension that needs to be put together to
to really fit with the with the problem
statement
I think the in the second one is is kind
of a delivery of that uh what I think
it's it's very clear and I think it's
another made the point about it is one
is about the cost of delivering this
product uh what I think Insurance have
not really been able to solve up to this
point is reducing that upfront cost of
matching the product and the customer
and together with it I think the other
one which kind of comes hand in hand is
actually trust so we sit here and we say
okay we kind of believe in Insurance the
insurance is a wonderful construct or a
pension we believe that if I put a
dollar today 50 years later I'll get a
pension I think for for most people in
in out there that that's the Gap that is
there and this is why you use
a variety of methods to educate to
business right products to match it to
the correct people so I think this is
the problem that definitely there is a
big steps in trying to experiment to
address it technology solves part of the
problem but technology doesn't address
the Techno the gap of trust they can
reduce we can reduce the fraction of
delivery of the product we can put it on
the phone but for somebody to trust that
there is going to be something there 50
years later that's a pretty big leap of
faith that's not that one of the trust
issue we have to deal with
you have to think like cash when I give
you a dollar bill you don't trust you
you don't have to worry about trust no
because you're holding that dollar bill
is good enough and that we call as a
bearer instrument trial in a cloud in a
fancy way of course token is nothing but
like a cash moment I hold that token I
don't care who gave it to me as long as
I'm holding a token right it's a legal
tender
you will trust me yeah this whole
verifiable credential is based on it
based on this construct of I don't need
to have a trust system and there's also
a generational switch going on here as
well right so my generation thinks if
I'm not holding the paper in my hand I
don't trust that it's going to happen
but my daughter's generation I mean I'm
technologically savvy enough right that
I understand this but as the Next
Generation comes along they don't care
about this they don't even know this
exists at some level because they pay
everything like this go ahead but
there's a problem with your paper
Behavior the paper is as good as the
institution which absolute the paper
absolutely but in the token world that
institution doesn't matter I agree
because the token has in encapsulated
both the value and ownership right so
this is the whole idea about
decentralization we can spend a lot of
time talking about D5 as well it's hard
for people to understand because they
went to speculation yeah but don't care
about speculation at all so I think he
made a good point trust yeah technology
can create a lot of data but who trusts
those data we are saying technology is
good the data becomes a
and token represent data ownership and
value so I want to make a point here I
spent my entire
Financial career
like employing technology to make
Financial Services transactions
have less friction the whole thing this
is what made me famous in Morgan Stanley
and Goldman Sachs we were able to go
from doing 100 million dollars of
business a day employing technology go
to a billion or two billion dollars a
day without blinking an eye we worked on
this forever but at the end of the day
no matter how much you automate what I
was doing which was sales trading or
trading if there was a problem
the human wanted to talk to another
human right it was your fault or you can
help me so how do we it's okay but today
complain of a cash problem when you're
holding a cash no no it's not to me
about cash or digital
philosophical perspective don't care
anybody in the room is holding a dollar
no no no no worrying about who gave it
to them no not don't care at all but
they do care if something doesn't work
yeah my question is always in the
digital world we see hacking happening
all the time we see all this stuff so my
real question isn't about the trust
anymore we've already established that
and I agree but the question is
how do we handle this hybrid situation
we're at the end of the day that's right
let the technology guys answer the
question I wasn't asking you it's a nice
back-end yeah let's delete that so so I
I think sorry just one one comment uh
in the end it's boils down to
standardization because actually it's
not a technology problem it's just
agreeing how people communicate and
exchange the information and this is fun
Foundation of efficiencies any efficient
system so as soon as we are able to
reach the critical mass the trust comes
with the experience you know more people
more volumes and naturally there will be
issues because this is the nature of the
technology unfortunately you know it's
for humans develop it so it has exactly
we passed the I think he's worried about
last yesterday 150 350 million dollar
hack happened in binance finance yeah so
I'm not worried about buying it I think
they'll be fine but I do think that
people at the end of the day have they
have questions and when they have
questions look I think that technology
is never going to replace humans it's
just not going to happen because in the
same way that I'd love to sit and have a
conversation with parul right until
until late at night that's never going
to go away but it also means that if I
have a problem with my insurance I want
to get Thomas on the phone to make sure
that I understand even the digital
transaction that's already happened that
I trust but I just want to make sure
that I get it and I don't think that's a
generational problem go ahead can I just
add a few things here can I break the
conversation up into two things go for
it warning is around the trust and the
customer trusting in the human touch and
the second is which is I think
completely politically incorrects
considering I'm sitting here is that why
is UOB all Prudential or Straits not
offering
pension Solutions long-term assets to
the people that we are talking to in
Asia Africa where the scale is so much
and the reason is the cost of pension
Administration is very expensive in
developed countries it is anywhere
between 85 dollars to hundred dollars a
year per customer in developing
countries including those in Latin
America it's anywhere between 35 to 50
dollars India works at twenty dollars
right so where is it a person who's
going to spend a saving of hundred
dollars a year is going to be paying 30
dollars in pension Administration right
that's when technology comes in so I
completely disagree with everybody
sitting on my left and right is that is
why technology comes in because pension
techs like us are providing aggregated
Asset Management to Mr Prudential in
Kenya who I work with by the way uh
where they are receiving ten dollars a
day from a million people and they are
getting aggregated 10 million Partners
to manage at data levels which are
disintegrated through and this and given
its smaller bite size by the pension
Tech platform that I have and hence it
becomes viable for them to manage the
money and give meaningful returns if it
was going to be the other way around the
cost of administration is very high so
what are they spending money on right if
they're taking 85 or 100 in developing
countries it's good to understand that
they're spending money on Advertising
they're spending money on awareness
they're spending money on marketing
they're spending money on
um
um on financial literacy and so on and
so forth but if all of that is broken
down to a smaller level where they don't
have to worry about all these things
because you're in a B2B to C model or
you're doing direct sales with the
persons that uh he's uh so plindu was
talking about in Ghana then you're as
good as the person standing in front of
the customers whether delivery is only
between that one to ten people and hence
the conversion rates are very high so
you don't have to look at pension
Administration only from a blanket color
of Television advertisements because
none of those farmers are looking at
those they're only trusting that person
sitting in front who's coming to talk to
them about it who's a person who lives
in the village whom they can go and talk
to and they're using things so we work
on a ussd phone you can do a staff 453
hash in Rwanda and open up your pension
accounts using digital you can use we
can embed ourselves in Bora Bora guys
apps and they can use it in their app
and we also do it on WhatsApp where I
don't have to worry about language
barriers I don't have to worry about and
everybody has WhatsApp on their phone
they send they're using it to do we even
do it through that you don't worry about
3G 4g5 it doesn't matter you don't
doesn't matter it doesn't matter at all
so the your delivery has to be the same
like they say the sachet model there is
no reason to Whatsapp in the sense poor
people do not need poor Solutions why do
you and I don't worry about these
technology services like you also said
your daughter's not worried about
anything on the phone why can why can
that same person not get the same
quality of services they trust
everything but we are not giving them
The Delivery Systems no we are we are
the ones who are sitting here we are not
giving it to them because it's not
financially viable for us so make it
financially viable yeah right find
solutions that are able to do it we run
a pension Tech and we do it we brought
our costs down to less than 10 percent
let the government do their part when in
India they ran these huge campus of I'm
going to say a few words in Hindi mutual
funds are here that means mutual funds
are the right thing to do and they got
the cricketers to do that so you don't
have to create public good to let people
know mutual funds are good investment
places NPS National pension systems it
is it is imperative that you have it
then they have these guys who are doing
this so now I don't have to go and
explain it to the project that we're
doing in Orissa with the smes to say
that you should be saving for your old
age because this public good is already
created so the trust is already created
so you really have to go out and see
sliced eyes and use technology to do it
if you don't do it the trust will never
be built you know talking about the
WhatsApp things he spoke about when we
went to Ghana
they did not want to log into a system
to get a token
it was a feedback from the ground we
were forced to design a product where
you get your code tokens by interacting
between two WhatsApp messages
sometimes low income segment forces a
design constraint which forces you to
think a better technology solution which
is awesome yeah and this is what
publicity is already it exists where all
pinbox is doing is we are the glue and
I'm very happy to be called up a glue
technology is all about that right and
that's the reason why all this is coming
together and today we don't use WhatsApp
only for servicing I use WhatsApp to
open accounts probably the only one
who's doing it so if Financial Health
is important which I completely agree
if we believe as well that as you get
wealthier you get healthier
and we're talking today about laws look
at the reverse I guess
well it's kind of both isn't it tell me
tell me tell me so you think as you get
healthier you get wealthier
[Music]
no no but you but I mean can we say I'm
asking right but can we say from
experience that in plural places people
are less healthy than wealthier people
even if just for Access yeah who cares
that wrong other reasons but the mental
health is different yeah I didn't say
that I didn't I'm not I'm not cause I'm
not talking about causality I'm just
talking about the facts yeah but if
that's if that's if that's the case at
that point yeah if that's the case
as people get wealthier they'll get
healthier as well globally yeah how does
that change the way the world looks from
a financial and a health Tech standpoint
in the context of everybody living to
100 years okay I think maybe there's a
slightly different
uh to to the point that you're asking
but if we think so we spend majority of
the time talking about the solution so
solution of pension and kind of really
focusing on how do we improve the
solution but actually the the other part
of this which the report I think
highlights is like people expected to
live to 100 years so I think there is
going to be a lot more awareness about
what happens after let's say I turn 60
and or 65 and you know I'm not as
capable of say working in the field I
think there is going to be a lot more
pain defined pain from the customer from
consumers or from Farmers or from
anybody because that seems to be that
combination because if I expect that
okay I'll be gone by 70 years old I
don't really need to worry about it
right just five years of kind of towards
the tail but I think so sometimes you
said this actually and I think it's
right is that the people with whom
they're interacting are now giving them
the better solution based on the tools
that they know they already have and I
think they're going to do this in the in
the health Tech space as well yeah but
this is just an introduction for us even
the health your question around Health
Tech with uh fintech or ensure Tech is
inevitable now yeah because we have
spoken to so many Health sector industry
and they have consistently gave us a
feedback that you got to bring your
financial product right into the or use
the word embed into the health services
industry yep today Health service
industry suffers from a clear separation
from the financial industry the same
thing we talked about at the beginning
right it's like in Singapore there's a
big project which Mas runs with uh with
which is bringing the Health Data
infrastructure together is critical many
countries are trying to bring the health
sector data together with the financial
sector data to create a better
opportunity for different Financial
product guys to plan better and and it's
absolutely just the challenge is you are
going to live longer our needs are
getting sharper the risks are also
getting sharper as you know transparency
is is actually at negative thing for
pricing Insurance transparency yeah if
more transparent more expensive is that
better for consumers yeah yeah so you
know so sometimes what you are trying to
get into is creates a challenge for the
industry because you have to put a
better a more itemizing open insurance
it's good for consumers yeah so so I
think that at this complexity to deal
with but I completely agree that today
Health sector if one thing excites me
from a future of fintech is to jump into
the health sector because that's where
the biggest opportunity lies for all the
fintech industry right so that's why I
asked that question because I think
those two things cannot be separated
right so I didn't want to say something
and we are getting the stage where for
the longest time it was a lot of
causalities when it comes to the
wellness information Wellness data but
no one was able to
prove actually the impact on the on the
health and and translated impact on the
insurance now we are getting the stage
where the amount of the information
actually experience Real World
Experience from different places
including the what Singapore government
has been naughty here because you know
my portfolio is down by 30 my mental
health is not good if that data is not
known by UOB I'm a bank I think they'll
have serious problems
so so sometimes that data say it can
cause its own problem absolutely so did
go ahead it goes back to the but
you see it's you can link to things yeah
my mental health and the exact portfolio
price going down exactly this goes back
to your initial our initial Point that's
wealth and health goes together they're
entangled you know like like in quantum
physics entanglement of the of the I
wish I didn't have that much money to
buy those products yeah
we're running out of time thank you all
for doing this and thank you to elavandi
and for Prudential for giving us the
space and the time to have this
conversation I thought it was awesome
thank you all for thank you thank you
thank you thank you very much thank you